so I've got a passage from the suitors
magic ayah 48 Kosambi suitor is there
the end of it it's the last few
paragraphs and have those quite a nice
description of the understanding of a
sex partner
mm-hmm so I thought my pee
so it's after the it's after the bit
where the Buddha's talking about what
what what leads to friendliness
cordiality the bhikkhus mmm-hmm Sangha
and he says these six things lead to you
know engaging these six things this
angle will be harmonious unity conquer
living in Concord and the last one is
having the right view sharing the wrong
view he says that see the peak that's
the most with fun remember that's the
fundamental oneness yeah everything else
is so secondary to that so then he says
and how bhikkhus does this view which is
notable leading on lead whoever acts on
this pond towards the correct
destruction of suffering here bhikkhus
are bhiku gone to the forest or gone to
the root of a tree or gone to an empty
dwelling reflects thus is there any
internal obsession or abandoned by me
because of which with this obsession I
can't understand I can't see the essence
of the obsessed mind if bhikkhus epic
who is obsessed by the passion of sense
desire there's just an obsessed mind if
bhikkhus are bhikkhus obsessed by he'll
will there is just an obsessed mind if a
bhikkhu is obsessed by sloth and torpor
or tiredness is sluggishness there is
just an obsessed mind if he's obsessed
by hesitation and remorse it's just an
obsessed noise
if he's obsessed by doubt there's just
an obsessed mind if a bicker is engaged
in thoughts about this world it's just
an obsessed mind if bicker is engaged in
thoughts about another world it's just
an obsessed mind if I pick you in bodies
of volcán quarrels disputes having fall
into an argument dwells stabbing others
with verbal Becker's there is just an
obsessed mind he understands in this way
there isn't any internal obsession on
abandoned by me because of which this
obsession with this obsession I can't
understand I can't see the essence of
the obsessed minds my mind is well
directed for the awakening of truths the
truth for him this first knowledge is
attained which is Noble well transcendence it's
which is Noble well transcendence it's
not shared by petitioners
that's the first one so what do all
those things have in common things as in
up the obsessions
yeah well the older the dog is an
obsession your will an obsession and
shouts is an obsession to think about
this was an obsession the other one has
an obsession yeah it's all right it's
all mine exactly so he's not and that's
that's it so it says there clearly it's
not he chased it down and analyzes doubt
chase it down analyzes sensuality here
he just knows this resulting obsession
of the mind
obsession is there he knows obsession as
obsession being there which means
understanding of the nature of the mind
nature of it not the content yeah yeah
not the experience ordered why this
special experience this
out-of-this-world experience not out of
this world experience experience or free
from lust with lust all of that is
secondary to the mind being first in
that sense yes understanding the nature
their mind means a surmounting anything
that can obsess their mind yeah so easy
so you talks that about these different
obsessions hmm but the point is that for
each one this is just an example of
obsessed mine yes the it's what they
have in common that's the most important
that's the thing is that you stop you
stop you stop trying to discern and
analyze the content yeah you just see
there's an example yeah of the nature
then you behind it that you want to
discern this and so only then will you
know will you be able to answer for
yourself that right there isn't a spot yeah
that right there isn't a spot yeah
otherwise you would know otherwise it's
not up to you if you're obsessed mod is
determined by presents of greed aversion
delusion or thoughts of this world
thought it means you will be effective
when those things are there but if you
develop your mind so when obsession of
you buddy it will is present the mind is
not upset by it so it will still there
the content is still the same yeah but
the mind is now not obsessed because
you've understood that whether there's
an obsessed mind all obsessed mind
because basically you refrain from
entertaining the further obsession
towards the content and you forced
yourself to look for the nature of it so
you stopped chasing down the individual
experiences and start understanding them
universally that's the whole point
because obsession does not it requires
maintenance it requires your involvement
so you requires you to choose basically
to feed it right and it's like when
people know like you know that or at
least you have the idea that suffering
is caused by craving not by adverse
circumstances you experience in the
world but when you experience the other
words let's say somebody comes and says
something upsetting to you so you know
they don't theoretical level you you
suffer cuz you're craving not because of
what they said but a practical level you
can't restrain yourself and you still go
after that person or whatever you cannot
help yourself but be obsessed about the
content that upset you and then same
when you meet agreeable experience the
prospect of sensuality you know the
excitement you are not developed in
regard to it you cannot help but be
obsessed so you choose to give in to
obsessions to present themselves which
means you choose to feed them
and that's why that's so like we in so
many talks that sense restraint is not
optional you want to be a sort of owner you need
you want to be a sort of owner you need
to develop that sense restraint to the
point that you are able to see the
nature of whatever is presently in front
of you in terms of the content of your
experience and not be obsessed by it and
I'll go after it and not be pulled by
saying yes or repelled by saying no to
sense restraints another way of
describing such as price would be
refusing know not are obsessive obsessed
good obsession or bad obsession doesn't
matter obsession is there and in order to do
obsession is there and in order to do
that so the sensory spent outlines your
mind yeah which then gets you to discern
what obsession actually is that's what I
was gonna say it seems to be like you're
talking about
it's a nimitta to see yeah the sign of
the month yeah yeah that's the necessary
the worse a prerequisite for a sort of
battle for the right view is to develop
sign of your mind see you tonight
which means able to transcend the
present enduring content that's pulling
you pushing you upsetting you obsessing
you and you still see beyond it in terms
of the mind that induced there
simultaneously here which is what all of
these different types of not have in
common yeah yeah exactly
so that's like it just seems to be that
one that's one knowledge they do it says
it like a so tapana can ask himself he
ponders he thinks okay can i am i aware
of the presence of obsessed mind or non
obsessed by exact and that's how by by
being being unable to be obsessed even
amidst obsessing circumstances obsessing
content that's how you become unable to
suffer even amid suffering messed with
the sandwich is begins with sotapanna so
you ask yourself am i free from
suffering in that sense would i not
suffer even while i'm experiencing that
which is suffering yeah that which is
disagreeable would my mind remain an
obsessed by it well would I fear it
would incline away from it will I try to
shout to myself when you try to protect
myself all of those that it should still
imply did you think suffering is there
so you're protecting yourself from it I
don't think it would a particular
wouldn't be able to consider that
question being else
well if transparent religion that
probably could the one that's not
avoiding responsibility or or mystifying
the content of his experience and that's
the whole point doesn't matter lie as I
said it's not only this doesn't only
refer to things that are not pleasant in
the nature that obsess your mind if you
just think they're Pleasant chasing all
the experience chasing those meditation
releases all of that is focused on the
content of it means you're completely
unaware of the nature unaware of the
nature means unaware of the mind
yeah unaware of the mind there is no
prerequisite for the right view yeah
doesn't matter how special your
experience might be so that's what I'm
saying before like that whole like an
oval affirming overly denying attitude
towards the content of your experience
and saying when we when we mention our
talks when people mystic of experience
and it's really it's not the experience
it's mystical it's their attitude that
miss defines it any experience is just
an experience just the content of the
senses or the mind as well yeah but it's your
or the mind as well yeah but it's your
attitude where the Miss defines whether
glorifies and values the content in
itself right that's why it's mystical
that's why it's a wrong view yeah not
what tricks but it see for as long as
you value what you experience what you
want to wear you might to that extent
you value the view of the content of
your experience not the nature of it but
it doesn't matter what you experience
what matters is where the mind is
obsessed by it or not and you can only
not be obsessed by it or affected time I
seem to make are seeing the nature yet
not by learning how to deal with content
perfectly yeah that's impossible so you
mean if you don't want to be free from
suffering you will be free from
suffering because that's the
automatically resolved of seeing nature
things you cannot suffer cause suffering
requires an obsession yeah you don't
need to then do something yeah
furthermore bhikkhus a noble disciple
reflect thus it's funny that in the
previous one who said he just said a
bhikkhu hmm
here cooker is a big hook I've gone to
the forest and there the rest of these
little chairs are all about a noble
disciple it reflects the reflects thus
pursuing developing making much of this
view do I gain calm some summit err for
myself mm-hmm do I gain extinguishment of
mm-hmm do I gain extinguishment of
myself hmm
he understands in this one pursuing
developing making much of this fuel I
gain calm for myself that game
extinguishment of myself Noguchi yeah
just further verify exactly what you
already know you already know that this
view this way of regarding things frees
you from obsessions which implies
inability to suffer so if I pursue that
view oh then the further calm comes out
of it and then the further
extinguishment of anything else in terms
of use and and habit they were rooted
upon greed aversion delusion it's the
second knowledge and then furthermore an
oboe disciple reflects those just as
aemond down with this for you are there
any other ascetics and Bravo Brahmans
outside here and down with such of you
he understands in this way no just
design madad with this view there aren't
any other ascetics abroad with outside
him down in this video the only way to
arrive at that view is to understand it
correctly which is only found within the
Buddhist instruction it's impossible and
see what that says well what that
implies is it's impossible to stumble
upon it spontaneously or accidentally so
even with like the before the bullet
Pacheco Buddhist even they don't stumble
upon it spontaneously they recognize the
value of their development they pursue
it and they free the mind in the same
sense that some assembled it yeah so
that's another sort of clear indication
of how I should not be changing your
experiences even if a spiritual nature
because that just because they happen to
you yeah understanding doesn't happen to you
yeah understanding doesn't happen to you
you develop it in regard to things that
happen to you but for as long as you
value things happening to you you will
not be understanding it it's mutually
exclusive you are either in the content
or you're refraining from valuing the
content and looking at the nature of it
furthermore a noble disciple reflects
those just as an individual who has
attained the right view is endowed with
a nature no usually a with a character
with a bow you know how he has a
particular nature am i in doubt with
such a nature in what way and in what
way BIC an individual who's attained the
right view endowed with such a nature
this is the nature of an individual has
attained the right view even though such
a one falls into an offense such that
the rehabilitation from the offense is
known still he quickly indicates
discloses clarifies to a teacher which
is wise component in the holy life hmm
having indicator disclosed clarified the
undergoes restraint to the future and
what does that mean
that means that the utmost personal
things personal wrongdoings cannot be
taken as personal anymore okay he
discloses it the only reason people
don't disclose things is because of the
involvement of the conceit yeah yeah
whatever fear what everybody so loot you
didn't sense of I am in regard to it
self view Southworth that comes out of
the self of you yeah and for somebody
with the right boots he's incapable of
taking it personally even things that
resulted like wrongdoings out of still
remnants of his personality his greed
his aversion his delusion yeah yeah but
he's unable to take it personally on
that fundamental level to not disclose
it or not see it as I thought that was
about doing yeah yes good so if you if
you if you recognize you've done
something wrong and then you have this
yeah you can start covering up start
making it opaque and not transparent
yeah yeah that's impossible so it's
impossible for a person with the right
view black person or mark doesn't matter
to become opaque again and lie to
himself about his own motives or doings
or actions it's impossible
so yeah there's the similar basis just
because just as a little young boy a
baby having stepped on a burning coal
with his hand or foot quickly moves back
in just this way bhikkhus this is the
nature of individual visit a review even
though he fall to a fancy quickly yeah
discloses indicates sort of immediately
that's the first reaction you know
there's nothing getting in the way of
him you know covering up covering it up
here so for him this is the fourth
knowledge this fourth knowledge is
attained which snowball beyond the world
shared not shared by petitioners
furthermore pic is a noble disciple
reflects than us just as an individual
who's attained the right view isn't out
of the nature am i endowed with such a
nature so it's the same same thing do I
have this nature
it says bhikkhus this is the nature of
individual who has attained the right
view even though he has become active in
terms of various duties with his
companions of the holy life mm-hmm
there's still a keen regard for training
in the high virtue for training in the
higher mind for training in the higher
understanding because just as a cow eats
the grass with a young calf and she
watches over her young calf in just this
way bhikkhus this is the nature min
evident of it to maintain the right view
even though he has become active in
terms of various duties he doesn't give
up training he doesn't lose the context
despite the other more mundane things he
might have to do that's what it means we
cannot forget the context of the right
view and the implicit development in it
and so on and the value its it cannot be
ignored so even even like back in the
sutras where well lay people became salt
upon us and then kind of chose to
continue living the household life
that's something they cannot forget yeah
which means throughout their life they
always thought but basically after the
review they would have felt at least the
degree of discrepancy between the value
of the review and development and what
they're doing is that it's also not
because they says that it's an obstacle
in that's another brother SEZ SEZ the
noble disciple you will sort of not
progress because fondness for work yeah
talk to economy may be okay yeah doesn't
matter the point is Noble the Sun yeah
and why lucky now this it is like you
might want about how would somebody
wasn't gonna not pursue further because
you even feel you don't have you don't
feel like you have to other people might
be like some people might be satisfied
with that the fact that you cannot
suffer amid suffering and everything
else is literally seven grains of sand
land and you know you know that there
are mountains of Himalayas that's how
much you've done already so it's like oh
this is nothing
and it's nothing from that point of view
but they're gonna said you know that
little is still something so that's why
you should do it yes yeah but some monk
said or maybe what would have just been
content with that and which would have
allowed him to live the life which
cannot be aligned with the right view
lalla cannot be aligned with the right
view yeah so if you choose to stay
alignment or as a big coup something so
this chose to basically not really
practice yeah that's against the right
view and you have to live that
discrepancy have like a layman in
clothes yeah you would you would feel
that discrepancy and sooner or later you
would have to basically you will turn
away from it yes so that's why saying
here's so even if you're doing that hmm
as this noble disciple you come again
you cannot and that's where they derive
you in clouds towards new bands slopes
to them that's its natural direction and
that's now you'd establish that and you
cannot not incline that way and it says
at most several lifetimes at most you
will have to go in abandoned by the end
of it and there's the only reason by the
way why sotapanna would sometimes take
seven lifetimes because they're not
because they are not practicing this
yeah so even with the utmost
non practice within several items you
would have to basically drain any
interest towards anything that's
that's discrepant with the right view
that's not compatible you would abandon
it but even if you're not practicing and
you're not behaving
you're behaving in a way that's sort of
contradicting you understand you still
understand you still have this knowledge
you stay yeah that's you cannot move
reflect as you go because then you know
why because it's not given to you like a
random special experiences that happen
and you don't know how or why yeah it's
because you understood the nature of
anything that arises for you here hence
whatever has the nature arising that's
why that nature is impermanent like
there always the the inside of sotapanna
in the suitors note with this special
thing arise arose for me I became sort
of and it's understanding the whatever
is of a nature to manifest that's why I
cannot be mine because it has manifested
like in this case it began with the
nature of the mind yes and that
understanding of their manifestation is
on the level of the level of the content
furthermore I know will disciple
reflects thus I think I was just quite
like this it's just these and you know
it's it's about these things that then
nobody ever thinks about hmm just as an
individual who's attained the right view
is endowed with strength a mind dad with
such strength and in what way bhikkhus
is an individual who has attained the
right view and doubt with such strength
because this is the strength of an
individual as to take the right view
whatever has been made known by the two
target so in this dhamma and discipline
while it's being taught
having heeded the meaning having
attended having a collective with
together with the whole mind lending an
ear he listens to the dhamma he
understands in this way just as an
individual does it take that's it mm-hmm
usually he listens to the Dhamma he
doesn't like well you cannot it doesn't
take effort for him to listen to the
Dhamma mm-hmm because his experience now
has been aligned with the universe'
principle of the Dhamma through his
understanding so whenever he comes
across the Dhamma
it's immediately that strength
they're that direct connection and even
that is not personal
yeah oh let me make the effort to think
about it and I could because when he my
sister damaged basically just he gets
reminded of what's already within his
experience scene and then again the next
one similar just as an individual who
has attained the right views endowed
with strength my endowed with such
strength what's the strength this
strength of an individual who has
attained right for you is this whatever
has been made known by the two targeter
in list island disciplines while it's
being taught he so loved translated this
as he he gets an experience of the
meaning he gets an experience of the
yeah dumbest yeah when it's being said
even if he doesn't think about the
Dhamma yeah what's being heard yes is
what he experiences as this direct
description of what he that's also why I
saw the panel will be able to tell
whether somebody has the review and also
whether somebody talks but somebody said
is aligned with the right view not even
if it's not coming from the Buddha if
somebody makes a statement he will be
able to tell whether that statement is
accurate or not
whether it's true or false based on the
experience based on the direct
experience of the meaning of that
statement the par leader is utter vada
and not about her and Dom abandoned
after Veda sama Veda and usually it's
translated as consumes religious Joey
remedy you know it's more like a
universal joy yeah I mean it might be
joy but you know when you understood
something for yourself and then you see
it in the world understood by others
okay yeah it already provides you with
joy even on a mundane level let alone on
the level of freedom from suffering and
somebody talks about freedom from
suffering you cannot not be joyous about
because it's Universal it's beyond you
in that sense cannot be taken personally
which is why even the joy you get from
it it's beyond your personality which is
why it's a joy that's
and that's we failed a list because
nothing wrong we like joy yeah like
people get experience joy when they stop
find somebody else sharing their central
preference like same taste in music in
whatever they get there Wow imagine
happens yeah yeah imagine how much more
when you find somebody also of talking
about freedom from suffering yeah
exactly how it is yes but that's a Joey
you can't crave for this craving
requires obsession requires personality
requires basically lack of that sight of
your own mind
then down in this way that's it and out
in this way you the seven factors the
nature of a noble disciple has been
properly considered the realization of
the fruit of stream entering in bhikkhus
endowed in this way with seven factors a
noble disciple is endowed with the fruit
of stream entry it seems to me it's like
the it's a description of the kind of
authentic questioning to the sex of
honor yeah yeah but it all starts with
depth aura transparent yeah why is the
considered sense restraint so as I said
doesn't matter if you wear robes or not
in order to discern the obsessed mind is
obsessed man you need to discern what
mine is you need to be able to withstand
the content of experience that has
manifested for you that is pulling you
pushing you distracting you not to deny
the content through this training the
loss of perspective through your action
because when you choose to act out the
content you forsake the perspective
towards the content so the only reason
why a layperson it's less likely to
become sotapanna today is because they
will need to deal more pain because of
the environment theory you don't include
the pain of sensory string because of
the sensory string you do the paint
because of the ba-ba-boom barment of
that which you are restrained against it
and today's lay environment is far more
proliferated with sensuality so sense
restraint is impossible it's only
because they can't build enough pain but
the only way to learn how to bear pain
is to start bearing the pain with you
and not give in so if it's too much well
you have an option either forsake the
value of sense restraint in which case
you forsaken the value of the right view
so then if you say you're practicing the
Dharma you're not doesn't matter what
you say yeah oh you could then maybe
change the environment if you can't
become a monk or a nun to the point that
you can really change the environment
that will suit and enable you at least
with there's some pain of that
without being overwhelmed by it well
then fine find something in between at
least we draw yourself to some extent
and then you will see how much you can
bear you don't know how much you can
bear if you never try to bear it which
means you're still acting out of
obsessions the words against both the
words and against confusion obsession of
doubt all of that but if you say a
person is able to to to withstand a
sense restraint to then reflect upon the
motivation behind your thoughts speech
and actions because when I'm in the
previous talk you mentioned sensor
States not just precept precept Adams
yeah clear this is what you don't do
well now self-restraint comes within
that oh do I need to look at this do it
not for the sake of saying no to
everything no no no I will not look I'll not sit I
no no no I will not look I'll not sit I
will not talk no just wanting to know
why where is this route to that yeah is
it within an obsession like do I feel
about the question to act towards this
it's already a formal obsession what's
the nature the mind yeah what's it like
what by discerning that obsession is the
underlying cause for your action yeah
you will then learn how to not act when
you're not obsessed yeah and when we and
sorry now to not act when you are very
obsessed exactly and when you're not
subside how to act yet his mother yeah
then you can act freely does nothing
exactly yeah but that comfort of knowing
doesn't matter requires you understand
so learning about obsession as an
underlying motivation you get to descend
the signs of your mind
yeah so you want to become a solo para
virtues necessary sense restraint in
regards and motivation of your action is
necessary enduring the obsession is
necessarily during the obsession and
developing strength but like in this
then we does that it forces you into
strength yet like Amelie strong enough
to I have the strength of somebody
exactly yeah if you're gonna have to
develop mister and you and your
obsession by not acting towards what
obsesses you not giving in to the
content yeah
just enduring the discomfort because and
that can also be a reflection itself
spend your entire day thinking or
keeping a corner of your eye at your
mind to see whether you're acting out
obsession or not that's it that's all
oh I'm sitting here talking and we're
obsessed with this as in joyful pressure
on account of this do you feel I need to
act or avoid or no okay fine
yeah but then you might change now I
feel like I must say all these things
oh so now you're obsessed so don't act
out obsession that's all you need to do
it's over
or I will say this I will not say no
just don't act out of obsession if you
don't do that whatever you say will not
be wrong isn't not another way of
describing the practice of sensor
strength yes yeah yeah of course but it's like
yes yeah yeah of course but it's like
another way of thinking about you know
how no sciencing just recognize when
obsession is present yeah another
October that's it
obsession pressure yeah contact